THE ELUSIVE SAMURAI
NORTHERN FRONT
MOCHIZUKI'S MAIN ARMY
Father…
-Ayako…
-Father…
To lose her father and the battle…
the pain in her heart
must be unfathomable…
So sad!
The incredibly cool Lord Mochizuki
has perished.
Mr. Mochizuki?
Yo! Chojumaru.
Father! I thought you were dead!
Your father is a phoenix, Ayako.
And thank you for coming!
Oh, my gosh! I'm so glad you're all right!
Ah, it hurts…
Father! Too much! You're breaking my ribs!
SQUEEEZE - CRACK
Don't be so fragile.
Us Mochizukis get stronger
with every cracked rib.
You should try it! Go on then!
-Like father, like daughter.
Hey, wait. Mr. Mochizuki.
Hmm?
You, Mr. Tokoiwa,
and your army are unharmed?
Did you all just not fight?
Did you just let the fort fall?
Yeah, that's right.
Holing up and fighting on the sly's
just not my style.
They can have the fort, for all I care.
You've got to be kidding!
NORTH
If this place falls,
things are going to get hectic.
At this rate, Ichikawa's army
will make their way south,
and we'll be severely disadvantaged
on the central and southern fronts!
SOUTH
CENTER
Wait.
We are entirely in his debt.
KITAJO MANOR MAGISTRATE
MUNEIE TOKOIWA
Our fort's defenses are weak,
and it cannot house a large army.
It wouldn't last two days
against an opponent like Ichikawa.
If Lord Mochizuki hadn't breached
their siege and let us escape,
not only would the fort have been
completely annihilated,
but so too would all of our troops.
So you see, kid.
We are a much bigger threat
to Ichikawa uninjured
and hiding out here in the mountains.
NORTH
MIDDLE
We can attack him at any time
from the rear
as he tries to make his way
to the central front.
Specifically, when he goes
to cross the river,
he'll essentially be a sitting duck.
I see.
So a coordinated pincer attack with
Shinomiya's army on the opposite shore
could be just
the devastating blow we need.
What a marvelous plan.
I'm assuming you've already made contact
with Mr. Shinomiya then?
Shinomiya?
So you haven't made contact with him!
But that means Ichikawa's going
to make it across the river, Father!
Which means Mr. Shinomiya is going
to be the one to get pincer attacked!
All right! I'm sorry, okay?
We only just got out from the fort.
I didn't have time to plan that far ahead!
-Father!
-We'd better hurry
and let Mr. Shinomiya know.
Yes. Ichikawa's army
will be on the move tomorrow morning.
Ayako. You stay here
and help defend your father.
But…
Starting tomorrow,
I'm leaving messenger duty for the
northern and central fronts to you too.
Now's your chance
to fight alongside your father.
Be a good daughter, and do him proud.
Certainly!
He may be helplessly lacking in stature,
but that Young Lord of yours
sure has the guts
to be a military commander.
Yes.
I'm finding myself more and more devoted
by the day.
It's becoming quite the hassle.
CENTRAL FRONT
SHINOMIYA'S MAIN ARMY
And so, Mr. Shinomiya,
could you please station some soldiers
at the exit to the northern mountains?
-Do it.
-Yes, my lord.
You need only spare a few.
Thank you, Mr. Messenger.
I'd love to hear more,
but you should rest in Hoshina's camp.
He's grown so much in just one year.
I can't wait to see what the future holds.
CENTRAL FRONT
HOSHINA'S MAIN ARMY
I can't eat any more…
Forward!
MOCHIZUKI
ICHIKAWA
SHINOMIYA - NEZU
PROVINCIAL OFFICIAL
MOCHIZUKI
HOSHINA
Mochizuki hasn't changed at all.
He is careless in his actions,
but somehow, things always seem
to work out for the better for him.
Now, with our newfound knowledge
of what's going on in the north,
we shall hold a war council meeting.
Sure enough, what is most important
for the central front now
is to defeat the provincial official.
I'd like to make it a quick
and decisive battle,
but we are evenly matched
with the provincial official's army,
and we do not have a trump card.
Is there any way out of this deadlock?
Mr. Nezu.
May I offer some advice
from the perspective of a messenger?
Fubuki.
What you were talking about yesterday.
We saw the fort in the south yesterday.
We believe the military forces
sent to the fort were somewhat excessive.
Excessive?
The fort is structurally sound.
If we can predict the direction
of their attack in advance,
we should be able to defend it with
Mr. Unno's army and a few extra soldiers.
We would need a large number of scouts
to pull it off,
but even an army at 80% capacity
would be sufficient.
UNNO'S ARMY + INUKAI'S ARMY
224 SOLDIERS
One, two, three, four, five…
BAD AT MATH
I see.
If we send the 50 remaining cavalrymen
to the central front,
they should be quite the valuable asset.
Fubuki.
Could Mr. Nezu not send in his hawk
to surveil the fort?
Of course!
Then we won't need so many scouts.
If we leave 100 cavalrymen in the south,
they can hold out for ten days.
A decisive battle of brief duration
also won't require as many reservists
at the fort.
So, in exchange
for sending Mr. Nezu south,
we could pull 200 troops from the south
to converge on the central front.
That is always a possibility.
Shizuku.
What a brilliant idea.
Thanks to Mr. Nezu,
we now know pretty much all of
the locations that need extra vigilance
on the central front.
You can leave any future fighting
to just us now.
Your suggestion makes perfect sense.
I feel a little ashamed to be taking
strategic advice from a child, but…
Shizuku.
It is advice coming from you. I know
that Lord Yorishige trusts you deeply.
Very well.
ICHIKAWA - MOCHIZUKI
SHINOMIYA + HOSHINA
The north will keep their army at bay
with a pincer attack,
I will trade places
with 200 men in the south,
and Hoshina's party will settle things
here in the center.
There are well over 500 men.
Chojumaru.
As messenger,
you must know many secret paths.
Let us make haste.
I need you to guide my path southward.
Yes, sir.
Shizuku has a lot of influence
over the chief vassals
due to her being a representative
of Mr. Yorishige.
Only she could come up
with such a bold idea
like shuffling the generals around.
TOKIYUKI
THE NEXT DAY
SOUTHERN FRONT - FUKASHI FORT
I sent 200 cavalrymen in secret
to the central front last night.
Mr. Nezu and I have also made
all the necessary arrangements
to help defend the fort.
I have a hawk watching the front,
but I can't keep him for long.
Please tell Hoshina
to have the battle on the central front
-finished within three days.
-Yes, sir!
Everyone, I bid you good luck.
The Young Lord is fascinating, Mr. Nezu.
Yes.
To think he enjoys the work
of darting about all the time.
He's a fine lad, I'll give him that,
but should we really be going ahead
with a child's strategy?
What are you getting at?
Defeating the provincial official's army
may only be a numbers game,
but Sadamune is a battle-hardened master.
Just as we have our plan,
he will surely have his own as well.
I want to go home.
Just how much have we been
running around these past few days?
Don't say that, Genba.
You've gotta stick with us.
There may come a time when
we need your power.
He's right though.
We are pushing ourselves.
The Young Lord
may be going too far this time.
Mr. Unno. Didn't you say
there were around 100 enemy troops
stationed to the north of the fort?
Yes. They have not moved
since the outbreak of this war.
They're not there.
There are no signs of the enemy there!
TOKIYUKI
SADAMUNE
It's them.
When did they get here?
So, the little restless messenger,
flitting about hither and thither,
was you all along.
Didn't I tell you
that if I saw you on the battlefield,
I would kill you without hesitation?
If I capture you, torture you,
and make you confess every single detail
relating to Suwa's instructions
and their involvement in the war,
not only will I win this war,
it will also give me just cause
to put an end to that Yorishige!
Go, men! All 100 of you!
Show them no mercy,
even if they are children!
With sword in hand,
all are equal on the battlefield!
Sever a limb or two if you have to.
Just make sure you capture them
in a state where they can still talk.
Brat! Kojiro! Abandon the horses!
They haven't fully closed in on us
from the right.
We'll climb the hill,
and make a run for it.
Right.
Ow! What is this?
-Why, you…
-What is this?
Another smokescreen from the fox, huh?
I've already seen that your smokescreen
has a limited range.
You'll be stepping out from the smoke
just around…
There!
Got him!
We got him!
This is bad…
They caught us.
We're finished.
Huh?
Who was that?
Who was that, you ask?
Well, I'll just have
to give you the answer.
Heaven's net has wide meshes,
but nothing escapes it.
For I am the guardian deity
of all of Shinano,
and nothing slips past my watch.
I am the Shinano Mask!
At your service!
-Yorishige.
Yorishige.
Allow me to explain!
The Shinano Mask is
the avatar of Shinano itself
who appears whenever danger is afoot!
At times tempestuous,
at times compassionate!
A higher supernatural being
who envelops all of Shinano
in his unconditional love!
He is a legendary hero,
a miracle, admired by all…
And standing beside him is
the king of commentary, Mr. Moritaka!
No matter which way you look at it,
that's just Yorishige Suwa!
The man's got "fishy business"
down to an art!
I am not! I am the Suwa Mask!
Now you've just called yourself Suwa!
Get your facts straight!
Since you remain unconvinced,
we'll just have to let the facts
speak for themselves.
In these turbulent times,
if you want proof
beyond all reasonable doubt,
you have to catch the culprit in the act.
Will you try, Sadamune?
Fall back!
Lord Sadamune!
We are evenly matched,
and we have the low ground.
Our position is not favorable.
Retreat! Retreat!
They gave up. Just like that.
I knew it. They're retreating east.
Just as I expected, Sadamune.
Sending 100 cavalrymen here
was killing two birds with one stone.
The primary objective
for Sadamune's 100 cavalrymen
was to provide backup
to the central front.
He saw that the southern front
was at a standstill,
and since he had
no immediate use for them,
he sent 100 of his cavalrymen
to the center.
He used the same strategy as us.
And his second objective.
Well, that would be you.
You're the shrine attendant
of Suwa Grand Shrine,
running about the battlefield
on a secret mission.
If he can capture you
and make you divulge everything,
that will give him the perfect excuse
to come after me.
He dispatched those 100 cavalrymen
not just to support the central front,
but also as a net to capture you.
Such a future suddenly came to me,
and I came running as fast as I could,
but things are going to become
far too dangerous going forward.
You've done enough, Lord Tokiyuki.
Let the others handle messenger duty
for now. We're going home.
Going home?
The farther I stray from Suwa,
and the more people
drawn into this battle,
the less accurate my prophecies become.
Now that Sadamune has realized
your strategic worth,
continuing messenger duty
is too dangerous.
No.
I think you should go home too.
You've worked yourself to the bone,
Young Lord.
What he said. You're exhausted,
and that's why
you didn't spot their ambush.
No. I don't want to go home. Not now.
Lord Tokiyuki.
Do you have any idea of the men
who make up the small reinforcements
of the Three Great Generals?
Every one of them believes
the day will come
when Suwa Myojin will rise to champion
the desperately suffering people
of Shinano.
Each and every one of them is willing
to put their life on the line
for this war.
But there is no need
for you to do the same.
Your health is vital
to the shogunate revival.
There is no need for you to be taking
such risks right now. Leave it for--
Don't you get it?
I want to be useful for you!
You bear the weight of destiny
on your shoulders,
but all I've been doing
is taking and taking
without ever giving anything back.
When I look out and see all our allies
united in their faith in you,
I feel like I'm finally
giving back to you,
and it makes me happy.
And even then, do we still have to return?
It should be me saying that.
Mr. Yorishige?
All right!
If you feel that deeply about it,
you can continue on with your duties.
But absolutely no fighting. I forbid it!
Focus on getting the message out,
and only watch over the battle
from the rear.
I will!
Good grief.
Please take 100
of Suwa Grand Shrine's finest cavalrymen
and head straight for the central front.
With this, the battle
is now completely even.
If you get the slightest sense of danger,
remember that you can always flee.
Thank you, Mr. Yorishige. I'll be back.
And there he goes.
To bear witness to how much you grow
day by day…
To receive such high praise…
It is I who have been taking and taking
without giving anything back.
-Attack!
CENTRAL FRONT
THE DECISIVE BATTLE
What of Ichikawa in the north?
We can pin him in place
for the entire day.
-Look out for the big, bad man!
-Since the Mochizuki army is doing a dirty
cleverly striking Ichikawa from the rear.
-Who is this?
-I see. That is reassuring.
And now, I must be off.
I'm off to join my father in battle.
Excellent. Now we can focus
all our efforts on the central front.
Mr. Messenger reports
that Hoshina is also dominating.
Let's settle this once and for all today.
Nice. They're pushing back nicely.
Yeah. I had a quick look around,
and both Hoshina's army
and Shinomiya's army
are in great fighting spirits.
With a battle this chaotic,
not even Sadamune's 100 cavalrymen
can tip the scale.
We can win this war.
What is that?
What?
What on earth is that?
A mikoshi?
I'll flatten you all into the ground,
you lawless scum!
Heave-ho! Heave-ho! Heave-ho!
Heave-ho!
Lord Hoshina! We must retreat
and re-establish ourselves--
You bastards!
I've gathered the biggest,
burliest men around,
paying them to carry my mikoshi
and serve as my bodyguards.
And I shall shoot them all
from right here,
in the safety of my own little box.
This is my very own battle mikoshi plan!
Hyaaah!
Let's go!
EPISODE 17 (YEAR 1335)
THE UNYIELDING